Hey there. Uh in this particular session
we are going to talk about uh how to
steer tables using TUSCa. But first
we'll uh understand uh what a table is
and uh how it is structured uh in TSA.
So what are the different column and row
attributes which you can use uh to steer
different elements inside the table and
then we'll talk about the different
action modes and then uh we'll also look
at some of uh the examples through which
you can steer different elements inside
a table and different ways using uh the
methods which are available uh in the
TSCA tbox module. So let's start uh with
the basics which is uh what is the table
structure. So this particular image uh
it shows you a typical table uh when you
create a module for a table and then you
pull it into the TSA uh T-Box test case.
Then uh this is the step where you will
see that uh it has got a table and then
uh it has typically got rows and columns
right. So a table structure generally
consists of uh two attributes which is
uh the column and the row. Then each row
or column uh could have several uh cells
and uh these cells then have different
attributes. Right? So there are
basically three parts to a table. Um so
one is the row then a row will have
several cells. Then there is a column
which will also have several cells.
Right. So, uh let's look at some of the
attributes uh which can be used here.
So, whether uh it is a row or a column
or a cell of a particular table. So,
using this dollar one uh you can
basically steer the first row or the
first column or the first cell of a
particular table.
Similarly, you can steer u any row, any
column or any cell position using this
dollar sign with the particular number.
Right? So, if I give uh dollar two, it
will uh do the second row. If I give
dollar three for a column, it will uh
steer the third column. And if I give uh
the fourth cell, then it will steer the
fourth cell. Right? So it basically
steers the specified row column cell
position which you give and your test
case. Then uh there's another attribute
called dollar last. Now this uh
basically steers the last row uh or
column or the cell of the table. Then uh
we have also got uh the dollar header.
Now this will steer uh a cell in the
table header. Then we have got the last
content row uh which steers the last
table row with value uh and then the
first empty row uh which will basically
steer the first table row without a
value. Right? So as you can see there
are multiple options here and these are
provided uh by TSA so that you can
easily steer uh different elements uh on
the table using different properties
basically right so whether it is based
on the position or whether it is based
on the header or whether it is based on
um some content which is present or uh
it's empty. So all the conditions um are
provided here and you can use this to
steer different uh cell
attributes. So uh now coming to
different action modes uh which are
present in the table. Now uh we have got
four different action modes. Now these
are pretty common to other uh objects as
well. But for a table uh we have got the
input action mode uh using which we can
enter a particular value and then uh we
have got the verify using which we can
verify a value or a property and then we
have got the constraint. Now this uh
will basically restrict your search
within the table. So you can define a
constraint on a particular column on a
particular row or or on a particular
cell. Right? Then uh we have got uh the
buffer. So this will basically buffer
the value of a cell, row or column and
then store it in a buffer variable. So
all these action modes can be used when
you are um steering any particular
table. Now let's talk about some of the
general properties which are part of um
a table control and then uh these
properties can be used to perform
different operations. Um and let's look
at all of these. So we have got the
column count. Now this will give you the
number of columns in the table. We have
got the row count which will give the
number of rows in the table. Uh we have
got column number and row number. Now
this is basically the index of the
selected column or row. Um and this is
obviously relative to the header column
or row.
Then uh we can also use the property row
column number to get the index of the
selected column. Similarly for um the
row we can use uh the raw row number
which will provide the index of selected
row. Now you will see a difference. Uh
both seem pretty similar column number
and row column number. But here the
difference is uh the header column which
starts at zero for column number. But if
you want to start at one then you can
use the raw column
number. Then we have got uh the result
count. Uh now this will return us the
number of cells which contains the
specified content. So this will further
help you uh to perform certain
operations like if you want to get the
total number of columns or total number
of rows or you want to select a
particular column or a row uh or you
want to get the number of cells uh with
specified content. So all of this can be
done using this table properties. So now
we have discussed u the action modes,
the properties and uh the table
structure. Let's look at some examples
um of how we can steer a particular
table using all of this um and then uh
we can basically automate our scenarios
uh in a particular table. Right? So for
this particular session we are going to
use uh this particular table. It's part
of uh the main obstacle page. Uh and
this is how a typical table looks like.
Right? So we have got the rows and we
have got the columns and then we have
got the cells. inside those cells we
have got some values and then uh we need
to steer this particular table uh to
automate our scenarios right so let's uh
go back to TUSCa and here um I have
already scanned this particular module
here as you can see so this is the
obstacle list uh control and it has got
a table which has got uh different rows
and columns right and then uh in the
properties section if you go to the
variable you will see uh we have also
got the header row. So we can also
define our own header row. So we just
need to change this value. If it is not
the first row then uh we can define it
anything here in the properties. So we
can change that right. So as you can see
the tag type is table which means uh it
is a table control.
So, uh let's go ahead and uh create a
new folder
here. And uh I'm going to call this
steer
tables. Inside this uh let's create a
test
case and let's call this table
steering. Okay.
And then inside this uh we are going to
pull our obstacle list module. So which
will contain the table as you can see.
So now uh let's look at our first
example which is to select a particular
row uh with a fixed position. Now what
do I mean is if uh we know the position
of a particular uh row and we want to
select a particular row or a particular
value in a particular row. So what I
mean is if we already know the row
number so which is fixed and uh it is
not going to change then we can use this
method to select any particular value
here. So for example I want to uh verify
whether the name of this third row is
not a table right so under the name this
is uh the value. So what I will do is
I'm going to copy this particular thing
here and then I'm going to come back
here and here uh we are going to select
uh this dollar with uh any particular
number here and uh we are going to
select the row number three here.
Okay. And then uh we are going to select
uh the particular cell. So it is under
the name right and here uh we are going
to give it a value. So let's go ahead
and give it a value and I've already
copied that. So this is the value not a
table. So we can go ahead and execute
this
now. Okay. So now in the scratchbook uh
if you look the test step has passed and
here if I go further into the table you
can see it selected the third row and
then uh it went into this particular
cell under the column which is the name
column and then uh it verified the value
right. So this is pretty uh simple and
easy. If you already know the row number
and uh it is not going to change then um
it's pretty straightforward. Right now
let's look at our second scenario and
here we are going to select a row by
using some values which are in specific
cells. So here we don't know the row
number but we know that uh there are
some values in particular cells using
that we will select uh or verify some
other value in that particular row.
Okay. So uh let's go ahead and do that.
So this I'm going to call this
fixed
position. Okay. And then um let's go
ahead and add another step here. So I'm
going to drag this
again. And here we are going to call
this
specific cell
value. Okay. Uh so now let's look at an
example how what we can do here. So now
u based on um these particular values
here right so we have got ID and we have
got a name. So either we can use one or
we can use both of them and uh I want to
verify the category. Okay. So let's take
this fun with tables and then uh we want
to verify the category is hard. Okay. So
either we can uh put a constraint on
this name or we can put a constraint on
the ID or we can use both. So let's uh
work out with just one constraint uh and
then let let's try to select a
particular value. So here uh either I
can use the ID or I can use the name
since it is unique I can go ahead and
use the name here. So I'll come back
here. I will go to a particular row. I
will select the cell here.
uh and I'm going to use the name uh I'll
put the value here. Now instead of
verify I'm going to put a constraint
here. Okay. So this is the way of uh
basically filtering out your search
based on some value. So TSA will search
for this value in um all the rows and
wherever it finds it will select that
particular row. Right? So that's how
this particular logic works. Now uh we
want
to see whether the category is uh
basically what is the expected category
here which is hard right. So based on
this constraint it will select the row
and then it will select the particular
cell and then it will verify the value
that's what it is going to do here. So
let's go ahead and run
this. Okay. So in the scratchbook uh now
you can see if you drill down the table
uh it has selected that particular row
based on the constraint and then it is
verifying that particular cell value
which is hard. Okay. So that's our
second scenario. Uh so selecting a row
based on a particular cell
value. Now uh the next one uh is pretty
similar to this. Okay. But instead of
constraint uh if we know that a
particular value is kind of unique in
that particular table or in all the rows
then we can directly use the row value
instead of uh selecting a constraint
because uh the constraint uh it will
take some time if you have got a large
table um toka will take some time to
filter out uh that results based on that
particular constraint. But uh if you
know that that particular value is
unique across all the rows then you
don't need to use the constraint. Right?
So uh I'm going to pull this table
here and then inside this row we can
directly put a value here. Right? So
let's try with this one or let's try
with this one since it's a different
category. So we'll use this weight a
moment
value.
Now as you can see uh it's unique across
all the rows. If it's not then it will
not work. In that case you have to use
two constraints instead of one. Right?
So u here the row value is wait a
moment. Now based on this it will select
a row. Okay. And then uh we can verify
any particular value here. So if you
want to verify the category
uh then we can just fill the value
here. So it's uh category is easy. Uh we
can also verify all the other values for
this particular row. So the main
challenge uh is to find the particular
row or column where you want to do a
verification for a particular cell
value. So the first step always remains
same. you need to uh select the
particular row and column based on some
search criteria. Right. So uh now uh we
can go ahead and execute
this. Okay. And uh as expected this also
passed. Uh if you drill down again uh
you will see the verification was
successful. Okay. So this is another way
uh of doing it. So this is based on a
particular row value. So we can say
specific
row
value. So uh let's move on to our next
scenario. In this uh we are going to
select a particular cell by index. Okay.
So let's go ahead and add another module
here. So we'll drag this and we will
name this uh
select cell by index.
And what we are going to do is we are
going to select uh this particular row
which is the second row here based on uh
the category value which is easy. Now
this is uh common across both the rows.
So we are telling Tosska to select the
second row which contains uh the value
category as easy right and we'll use a
constraint to basically filter out these
rows and then we'll select the second
index which is the second row with the
same value right so here uh in the row
instead of dollar we are going to use
something called hash symbol and then we
are going to use the two which is the
index two inside this uh we are going to
use the dollar symbol and uh we going to
say the second cell. Uh but this will be
a constraint and the constraint would be
the category which is easy right? Uh
actually it is the third cell not the
second and then here uh we will choose
the second one and
uh and we will verify the name which is
twins. Okay. And then let's go ahead and
execute
this. So as you can see uh the test
passed and if you drill down again uh
you can go into the log info where you
can see the expected and the actual
value. So this is how you can select any
particular cell uh by using uh the
index. Right? So let's move forward and
let's try to use some other properties
uh which could be useful in some
scenarios like uh getting the count of
uh the number of rows or the columns or
selecting any particular cell. So uh
let's go ahead and add another module
here and let's calculate or let's verify
the row count of a particular table and
that we can do using uh the property
which we already discussed which is the
row count right. So here uh in the value
of the table we can put down the
property name which is row count and
then the value uh for example this is 12
uh and I'm still looking at the same
table and uh instead of select we will
change this to verify. Okay so this
verification will be done directly at
the table control level. So let's go
ahead and try to run
this. Okay, as you can see uh in the
scratchbook results that uh the value
has been verified and uh it was a
success. Obviously we will not get
anything in the log info like other
verifications but uh it has done this
verification. So similarly you can also
uh do the column count here.
Okay. Um,
and let's change the value to 10. I
haven't counted the number of columns
here, so it might fail. But, uh, we will
see uh if it fails or
passes. Okay. Um, so expectedly it
failed. Uh, the reason is uh this
particular table has got around nine
columns, right? So uh but uh we can use
this properties to verify the row and
column count. Right. So let me change
this step name to row column
count. Okay. And let's move on. Um
obviously I can correct this and I can
rerun this always. Okay. And it should
pass the second time around.
So uh the next thing which we can do is
uh saving the value of a particular cell
to a buffer right. So for that again
we'll add the module
here. Okay. So here what we will do is
we will select a particular column. So
uh let's choose maybe um the name. Okay.
And then uh we will choose a particular
cell number. Right. So let's choose
anything. Let's choose five. Uh we don't
know what kind what cell value it has
but I want to buffer this and I want to
save this. Right. So I'll choose the
text property here. Okay. Then I will uh
save it to some
b name. So this is the buffer name.
So if it uh is able to select this and
then it is able to get that text value
it will save it in this particular
buffer. So let's go ahead and run
this. Okay. So as you can see uh the
test has passed and let's see what value
it is stored in this particular buffer.
So p_name has got the value fun with
tables right and if I look at my table
this is uh the fifth one which is fun
with tables. So I can buffer out any
particular value from this particular
table using this particular method.
Okay. And uh if you want to see the
buffer as well so it will be available
in the buffer viewer.
Okay. So these are some of the different
operations which you can do using
different properties uh and different
methods which are present in TUSCa. Uh
this is part of the TBOX uh table
control and once you add that control
then you will have access to all these
properties and using different action
modes along with the properties and the
attributes you can uh
basically steer u any table and any cell
or any column or